Hello, welcome everyone. This is active
inference model stream number 20.1 on
January 30th, 2026
and we will be discussing learning
extreme models with a coupled free
energy by Kendrick Nelson here and
colleagues. So Kendrick thanks a lot for
joining. you will provide a presentation
and if anyone is watching live feel free
to put any questions in the live chat
and I will read them when we have a
discussion. So thanks again for joining
and to you for the presentation.
>> Thank you Daniel really appreciate you
hosting this talk. Uh folk has been
doing a deep dive into active inference
including reading the the new book
that's come out in the last few years.
And so we're looking forward to talking
with your community about our own work
in modeling ex um extremes and how that
can be used to improve artificial
intelligence.
Uh my colleagues that worked on this
presentation with me are Igor Alivea
from Brazil and Amina Al- Najafi from
Iraq. Um and
uh and so um I'm what I'm going to go
through is sort of an introduction to
complex systems and why they have you
properties that are unique in terms of
trying to do modeling in AI. Um and then
I'm going to go through um a variety of
entropy measures including the standard
ones of the Shannon entropy but also
generalizations that apply to complex
systems and then show why there's a
unique one uh that I call the coupled
entropy and how we can use that in
variational inference to generalize the
free energy function and thereby be able
to model quite extreme um environ
irements and their distributions and
we'll go over some machine learning
about um results for that and then I
look forward to discussing it with you
and uh the community.
So fauk is um building capabilities and
riskaware intelligence. Uh there's a
couple aspects of that. There's a
technical aspect which I'm going to
brief today with regard to our work in
machine learning and risk risk. Um
there's also a DAO governance piece in
terms of using ideas from complex
systems regarding how you uh design
protocols for communities to make good
decisions. And then we see these two
threads coming together in terms of how
we can better mitigate um extreme risks
like uh the issues around climate
change.
Uh the team is diverse. I'm I'm in the
Cambridge, Massachusetts area. Uh but we
have um working partners around the
globe and then we also collaborate with
universities. Um I was on the faculty at
Boston University collaborating with
Mark Khan for several years and Eugene
Stanley and then I have also
collaborated with Sabir Yummer at the
University of New Haven and then we have
several other uh university partners. I
was in Turkey uh for two months this
year collaborating with Uger Turknali
which was a fantastic opportunity.
So here's the challenge um when when it
comes to catastrophic risk we know that
it's that um those very low probability
events that have high impact that are a
real concern. But machine learning has
grown out of traditions in statistics
that revolve around what's called the
exponential family and the Gaussian
being the most popular um example of
that. And even the metrics based are
based on the inverse of that which is
the logarithmic function that gives us
the maximum likelihood metric that gives
us the Boltzman gives Shannon entropy.
But these distributions and these
metrics don't really account for uh the
heavy tailed properties and the
nonlinear properties that we experience
in complex systems. and they're quite
difficult because the moments can
diverge. Uh so there can be situations
where you can't measure the variance um
which is the most common thing that
you're trying to characterize in in
machine learning. So we need ways um to
account for this. And just just as one
example to visualize this um you know
the cryptocurrency space um is one of
the areas that we work in as a community
and Bitcoin is notoriously very volatile
and you can see that in these spikes
that are not modeled by a Gaussian
distribution. Um here we have in the
middle an agent-based model where in red
you would see something like a Gaussian
process and you can see that yes there's
noise but there's not these large
fluctuations
but we can model u these with a
distribution that I refer to as the
coupled Gaussian and the coupling has to
do with the fact that I we can map the
tail decay shape to the source of
nonlinearity ity in the system and I'm
going to go into more detail about that.
Um so [snorts] we're generalizing the
exponential family and just um to remind
people what that is. First of all of
course it evolves around the exponential
function and then you have a set of
parameters that are dot multiplied with
a set of statistics. the traditional
ones being just x and x squared.
There can be some other terms that
involve x uh but we'll typically just
set that h to one for today's
discussion. And then all of this is
normalized by what's called the
partition function.
When we go to the coupled exponential
family, what we're doing is we're
modifying this exponential function to
be a power law type of function. And I
show that here. So this coupled
exponential, I'll highlight it right
here. Oops, I got ahead of myself. Um,
[clears throat]
it multiplies the variable by this
coupling, adds one, and then
renormalizes
or rather takes it to a power one over
the coupling. And that plus one is a
critical feature of the math. That's
what enables it to converge back to the
exponential. But it's also what
complicates things in terms of analysis
of nonlinear systems.
Now we keep the statistic and the
parameters.
Um and there's an additional factor
here. This 1 + d kappa has to do with
the the change from a cumulative
distribution. When you take the
derivative uh you get this additional
parameter in the exponent.
The most common distributions that we'll
talk about today are the generalized
paro distribution which I refer to as
the coupled exponential. That's when
this alpha term is equal to one and the
student t distribution when alpha is
equal to two and I refer to that as a
coupled gaussian. The critical thing is
that the moments diverge. Um and this as
this coupling grows more and more of the
moments diverge. And I'll I'll go into
more detail of that as we go forward.
But um taking a look at an example here
that's going to be used a lot in machine
learning because this is the
distribution that will you know be our
latent distribution is the coupled
Gaussian. So in black here you'll see
the traditional bell curve with the
coupling equal to zero. That's your
Gaussian
and that's what traditional machine
learning algorithms are built around. In
blue is what's called a compact support
distribution where it actually decays
faster and truncates. I'm not going to
talk a lot about that today, but that
would be a negative uh coupling. And
then what we're really focused on is
these heavytail distributions. In this
case, the one in red has a coupling of
one, which is the Koshy distribution.
And the critical insight in defining
this family is that the shape that tail
shape parameter is exactly equal to the
nonlinear statistical coupling or the
source of nonlinearity in the system and
these are proportional to a measure of
complexity of the system. So we're going
to show that we can model now the most
extreme complex uh systems with these
techniques.
One of the early insights about this
work that I showed in a paper several
years ago um that actually introduced
the coupled entropy function was a
concept of an average density. So it's
people are fairly familiar that the
center of a distribution is the mean and
that the variation is expressed for the
Gaussian as the standard deviation and
more generally for these non-exponential
distributions it's referred to as a
scale.
But
people have a difficult time uh
conceptualizing what entropy is
measuring. You should think of entropy
as the measurement of uncertainty along
the yaxis of a distribution. And you can
always take the entropy which is in the
log space, take the inverse of that, the
exponential, and bring it back to the
probability space. When you do that, you
you [clears throat] get a function that
I refer to as the average density of the
distribution.
And this is a translation of a
generalized entropy function. And what
the key thing here is that that average
density always lines up at the scale.
This is the invariant. And so this
particular scale of the distribution has
a number of things that are unique about
it.
Um, and in particular, what I've proven
this past year is that while there's
literally dozens of candidates for
generalizing the Boltzman Gibbs Shannon
entropy,
there has during this 50-year period of
development in the modeling of complex
systems been a missing requirement. And
that requirement is that your
generalized entropy has to be a measure
of this particular point of the
distribution where you have what I call
the information scale. And the reason
that's important is because that
point in the distribution is sensitive
to the linear sources of uncertainty
whereas the tail decay is sensitive to
the nonlinear sources of entropy of
uncertainty. And these two parameters
are the only way to precisely separate
those the role of linear and nonlinear
processes.
So let's take a closer look. This is
these distributions here are from the
family of the coupled exponentials or
the generalized paro distribution. So if
we start at the top, this is one of
those compact support distributions and
we can see it for two different um
parameters of the scale. On the top the
scale is equal to two and on the bottom
the scale is equal to half. And you can
see here clearly how it truncates.
Um now [clears throat]
the Boltsman gives Shannon is in that
case lower than this scale point and
when and when we go to heavy tail these
lower curves what happens is the
Boltzman gives
gets its probability gets very low and
that is to say its entropy gets very
high and it becomes dominated by the
tail shape and you lose sensitivity to
this scale parameter. So this is what
motivates the need for a generalization.
And the first um significant
generalization was done in the 1950s
and60s by Alfred Renee where he showed
that you could match a generalized mean
to that tail shape
and then still take the natural
logarithm and get a very effective
measurement of uncertainty in these
complex systems. And indeed it's a good
metric. it's it's used quite a lot um in
machine learning and in other
applications
but it doesn't match up with this what
I'm saying is a requirement here to
actually measure the the shape the the
uncertainty right at this scale
there is another significant proposal
that dates back to 1988 and has gotten a
lot of attention recently known as the
solace entropy
um it introduces a concept that I'm
going to talk about more that's quite
important called an independent equals
distribution.
However, I've since proven that it is
not in fact the correct function for
generalizing entropy. Um, and there's a
missing piece to it that was left out.
But if you look at this requirement,
um, this is what I'll show is equal to
this coupled entropy that I've defined.
I'm going to show that in a moment. But
the but the fascinating thing about this
is that the solution right along this
scale
is equal to 1 plus a generalized
logarithm of the scale. And and this is
the beauty of it and this was sort of
the Eureka moment when I saw this
solution that I realized that there is
something quite unique about the coupled
entropy and about this requirement
because now I'm maintaining in my
entropy function a a a dominant metric
about this scale parameter and the only
thing I'm doing is I'm changing what
logarithm function is measuring that. So
let's dig into it a little bit more and
see what is the where this function
comes from.
So as I said we start with a coupled
exponential function that forms these
non-exponential family of distributions
and then we take the inverse of that to
form the metrics uh known as the coupled
logarithm. And here you can see clearly
that the coupling is directly that power
and there's a minus one in order for it
to converge properly and there's a
normalization.
Now when we go to forming
the entropy function there's some
additional features that have to come
into this. So the first thing you'll see
is that this generalized logarithm now
is the coupling times alpha. You can
think of alpha as the shape near the
location of the distribution. So again
the most common ones is one for the
exponential distributions, two for the
Gaussians, but it can be a real number.
The other critical piece and this is
what was left out of the formation of
the solace entropy is that [snorts] you
can't just take this natur this
generalized logarithm of the
probabilities. You have to account for
how dimensions affect uh the metric. And
this again has to do with the fact that
you can think of the coupled logarithm
and the coupled exponential being
appropriate
with the cumulative distributions.
But once you take a derivative
uh you have to account for additional
terms in the exponent and each d each
dimension
involves another derivative. So you get
this factor here that you have to raise
the probabilities to.
Now this term in the right this
generalized logarithm
um let me go back that is exactly equal
to the inverse of this um generalized
exponential and so what that gives you
is the interior of this and you can
bring this inside the parenthesis too
I'm not going to show that today but
basically you're going to get um the
argument of this distribution
however However, that's not enough.
There's another piece here that pulls
the whole thing together, and that is
that you do not average over the
distribution itself. you average over
something that's uh I refer to as the
independent equals uh distribution
because what this is modeling is
how many random variables are um sort of
independent but equal to each other and
this is the metric that will give you
the parameters of that distribution. So
this is the this is the proper statistic
that function I can show here. It's it's
taking the original distribution P and
raising it to this power and then
renormalizing.
And the effect of this particularly all
the way here on the right is that it
reduces the original coupling value. So
now I have a modified coupling value and
the ca the critical thing is that as you
go to infinity
you always you know for for alpha equal
to two is the case we're going to be
most interested in this will converge to
a half and that half is the boundary
where the distribution would go to
infinite variance. So, so now what I
have is this balanced metric in which
I'm going to put a very high penalty on
low probability events through this
generalized logarithm. But at the same
time, I'm going to sample over a
distribution that makes sure that those
rare events don't occur too often.
So let's see what the impact of this is
now on variational inference.
Um if you know Dan if there's been any
questions in the chat this would be a
good place to break and and maybe answer
some questions. Um
>> let me just ask one clarifying question.
What is coupled what is coupled to what?
>> Yeah. Okay. Excellent question. So I
originally coined this phrase nonlinear
statistical coupling because you can
think of it as
treating the states of a distribution as
not being independent from each other
but rather the states are coupled
together. Um it comes out explicitly
from this um coupled exponential dis
this independent equals distribution.
You can kind of rearrange this function
and show that it's also equal to
multiplying all of the states together
where you have the state you're
interested in but the other states are
raised to this power.
Now since then what's become more
uh relevant is the fact that this
coupling term is the source of
nonlinearity in the system. So a classic
example which I'm not going to show
today but is very relevant to the
fluctuations in Bitcoin is
multiplicative noise. So um our our line
when we study linear systems we
typically have a deterministic component
that we're trying to learn and then we
model say the Gaussian noise as being
additive.
But in complex systems you're going to
have a third term in which the
deterministic process and the noise
process are multiplied together.
and you can show that um the coefficient
on that third term is equal to this
coupling.
>> Okay, so just to kind of echo that back
in a Gaussian mixture model, whether you
have just one Gaussian or multiple
Gaussians, you're superimposing
different means and variances, but the
variances never interact. It's just kind
of like you're stacking a bunch of
Gaussians on top of each other. Whereas
here we can get something that's looking
more like multiplicative noise because
of this multip um coupling that that
extends the tails of the distributions
and
>> yes
>> and I guess maybe address it at the end
or when right but how do we know how
much to inflate those tales when
how do we calibrate that factor to
empirical ical data and how would that
differ in its calibration or or
precision or recall than just using one
of these other traditional heavy tail
distributions.
>> Yeah. All right. So I that's a good I'll
answer that now as a preview of where
we're going to go with the talk. Um so
one thing we haven't shown all of this
but I would argue that this coupled
exponential family has the ability to
model any heavy tailed distribution
because what I'm doing is that coupling
parameter is um the asmtoic tail decay.
So you can figure out what that is and
then the parameters and statistics
measure are measurements of all all
that's happening in the distribution in
between.
So there's not a limitation in what
kinds of distributions you can model
with this method.
That's number one. Number two is a very
tricky question. Um, I'm going to talk
about the fact that the way I see it,
there's kind of two purposes for the
coupling, two or three. Um, the first,
as you're describing, is the system
itself that you're trying to learn can
have these fluctuations, and you're
going to want to characterize that and
then use that. In the way we're doing it
right now, it's a hyper parameter, but
you can you can analyze the data and and
determine a tail that fits to the data
you're interested in. That's one. But I
think actually the more important thing
is a way to make systems robust because
whenever we train, we always have
limited data and we also also have data
that might not exactly fit what we know
we're going to experience out in the
field. So uh we can also use this tail
decay as a way to improve the robustness
against things that weren't in the
training set. So there's these two
components to how you will use the tail.
All right, with that I'll press forward.
Um, so we're particularly interested in
how we can apply this to variational
inference and active inference. So
variational inference is a basian
learning method where we try to
approximate a complex true posterior
distribution with a a tractable
distribution where we're going to uh
learn the parameters of that
distribution and the goal is to minimize
the divergence between the true
posterior and the and the approximate
model.
Now recently and what Daniel is uh and
his team at the active inference
institute is focused on is that this
basic framework has now been applied
much more broadly to neuroscience,
artificial intelligence and even uh
socioeconomic
problems
where you can think of every single node
in a neural network as doing a
comparison between a top- down
prediction
or a bottomup observation and then the
difference becomes a way to um build an
inference model as you optimize and
minimize those differences. Likewise,
you can apply this to actions and
policies by using the prior or the prior
top down um as a preference of what you
want to have happen and then the
observations are now expected
observations
and then that can be that can control uh
the actions of a system.
So the challenge is how can we modify
the cost function this EV evidence lower
bound or the negative free energy uh to
be able to learn heavy tailed
distributions.
Um so let's we're in our own experiments
to date we've been using the variational
autoenccoder as a foundation for the
experiments. So let me just go over what
that is. Um here you can take a complex
data set such as uh the celeb a uh
photographs and you use a neural network
to encode a mean and a coariance matrix.
Again, in the standard VAE, this is a
Gaussian or or a mixture of Gaussians
that you're modeling in the latent
space. And then you can sample from that
in or decode it in order to get a new
sample generated.
And the thing that you're optimizing
here is what's called the negative elbow
or the free energy. It has two
components. It measures the quality of
the reconstruction and it measures how
simple um your latent space was in terms
of staying constrained to traditionally
a mean vector of zero and a coariance of
one.
Now uh we can generalize this and what
we do now is we're going to use a
coupled Gaussian and then we're going to
match that coupling with a metric which
is the coupled free energy and it turns
out while the derivations are
complicated in the end we get out the
same metrics that are used traditionally
with some additional coefficients. So if
we assume the pixels are continuous
approximately
then um uh well let me start actually
the latent layer then is measuring the
divergence and that's basically just the
trace over the um co the the what's now
called the correlation metrics and then
also the differences in the means
between the prior distribution and the
posterior distribution.
So that's one component and that is a
just a calculation
and then uh we also measure the mean
square average and again this isn't
changed it's just some coefficients that
have changed it's it turns out we still
get the same metric but now what happens
is because we have this heavy tailed
distribution as the model
um we're this mean squared average is
going to be highly sensitive to what's
happening in the tails.
And the way we balance that now is that
rather than sampling the latent space
directly, we rather sample this
independent equals modification to it.
And this is the real innovation that's
made a big difference. Now um and again
what happens is as the coupling of the
Gaussian goes to infinity
the coupling of the samples we're going
to generate is limited to less to be
less than 1/2. So we always guarantee
that there's a well- definfined mean and
variance uh from the samples that we're
uh drawing from.
So let's see how this works. show a
couple of pictures of this. So on the
left I have um a log linear plot and
then on the right is the log log plots.
And if we start with this light blue
curve that looks like a parabola here
this is the Gaussian and the coupling is
10 the minus 5 which is essentially zero
and the modification doesn't really
change that at all. It's still just 10
the minus 5. And again, we see this
Gaussian here as a knee on the log curve
and a very sharp decay of the
exponential.
Then if we go to a Koshy distribution in
this dark darker blue, we see this very
flat tail curve here and you see the
longer tail here on the log log plot,
but the knee is still in the same place.
Now when we take that independent equals
curve
um we have a much softer decay or excuse
me we have a much faster decay here. Now
the coupling is 1/3 and again that's
less than a half which is the critical
point here. So we took a distribution
the Koshy that h doesn't have a defined
mean
the variance is infinite and we modified
it into a distribution that's well
behaved and again so we see that as this
sharper curve here on the log log plot
and then finally we can go all the way
to the extreme of a distribution with 10
to the five coupling.
There's not necessarily practical use
cases for s such an extreme distribution
but the point that we can actually still
have convergent learning with such an
extreme distribution is a unique
capability. So we start with this sharp
spike here, this very long tail.
But both the coupling and the um
correlation matrix get modified such
that the modification is more like a
delta function here showed here in red
with the dash. And you can see that on
the right here the very sharp turn here
has to do with the fact that the
coupling is so high. But now um we have
a curve that's more balanced here at the
top. And again this uh new curve or
distribution has approximately 1/2 as
its coupling value.
So what does that enable us to do? Um
going back to this example of modeling
the Bitcoin returns
in traditional machine learning with the
uh CVAE we would be using a Gaussian as
the model and it's it's a mixture so
it's going to get a little bit of the
tail but ultimately it fails to capture
these extreme elements of the Bitcoin
log returns. Um so the blue is the
actual data and then this sort of um
orangey gray color is um the model. If
we set our coupling to be 6 which we
measured to be approximately what that
uh particular
uh set of data was characterized by. Now
we can see that we do have uh samples
all the way out into these extreme
tails. And so this is the key point here
now is that we can we can now have a way
to model and learn um these extreme
distributions. Now to date we we'll make
progress on this but to date the
coupling is a hyperparameter
um that we're setting a priority to the
training and that but what is important
is that we can then learn that
correlation matrix um to fit uh the
data.
Is this still overd dispersed
on the Bitcoin there?
>> The model isn't perfect if that's what
you're referring to. Um so yes, it you
know um it does look like we're getting
um some charact some samples that are
further out than what the data was.
Is that what you mean? But
>> yeah, and and then and then again just
how would this differ than than an
inflated tail?
>> Was it does it have a different
computational requirement or does it
just move probability density from a
central tendency
>> out to a tail in a way that has a
certain um I guess curtosis.
>> Yeah. So let me let me talk about that
in two ways. If we stayed with the
Gaussian distribution,
uh the problem is that we would end up
with this very fat distribution
potentially like if we really wanted to
capture this sample out here, we'd have
to have a very fat standard deviation
and then that would mischaracterize the
fact that most of the samples are in
near the mean. Um, if you go, let's see,
if I go all the way back
to this curve,
we often talk about the tail being
slower, but another feature of these
heavy tail distributions is that around
the mean, it's more spiky. So, there's a
lot of mass near the mean and then it
spreads out. And so what h so so it's
both of these characteristics that you
want to be able to capture in your
model. So that's one aspect. So the
Gaussian isn't going to be able to do
this. Now there's a second question.
Oh, is the the second point is the
following and maybe the easiest graph to
show this is if I go to this graph here
the question might arise why can't I
just use a heavy tail distribution in
the latent space but keep the Shannon
entropy metric right well the problem is
what happens is
that the Shannon metric is going to be
so sensitive to
uh the uncertainty caused by the tail
that it will not have any un it will not
be sensitive to the scale which is what
you're trying to learn and modify the
parameters of in your neural network.
Um and in particular what happens even
when so I'll go one other thing here in
the early work we have a paper we're
we're writing a new paper on this
currently there's a paper that we
published around 2020
on the coupled VAE where we used the
generalized logarithm but we sampled
from the latent distribution we didn't
really use this part of the function
And what we found there is we were
limited to around a coupling value of
0.5 to one. And as you tried to go to
higher values of coupling, the training
process just wouldn't converge. Uh so
eventually you'd get um such extreme
measurements that the training process
would just crash and and you wouldn't
have any learning process at all.
And so to date, the state-of-the-art is
that yes, you can train heavy tail
distributions, but typically they're
limited to distributions that are of uh
faster decay than the Koshy
distribution, you know, which is
coupling equal to one. And it really
doesn't work very reliably unless the
coupling is less than 0.5.
And I I'll just jump ahead here. What
we're showing now is that even in this
most extreme case of 10 to the fifth
where you can I'm not convinced that it
has practical value but it still
converges. I still get a a neural
network with a model. Um so this is
showing now um
let me let me just back up a second. So
we're we're doing this test over the um
celeb a data set uh where we have
hundreds of thousands of images of
celebrities.
Um and again the key thing here is that
in this latent distribute I'm going to
learn the latent distribution and after
the training I am going to sample from
that latent distribution directly but
during the training process I'm going to
sample from this modified distribution
to guarantee that the training process
converges.
Um and we show that in fact it does. Um
so against this metric of the coupled
free energy we get continual improvement
as we um increase the coupling all the
way up to 10^ the 5 and at 10 to the 5
it's just a flat line here. Now there is
a caveat that
um
this is not a onetoone comparison
because
we're modifying the model and we're
modifying the metric. Um but the
important thing is is we do show that
you know the amount of variation we get
as we as we increase this coupling value
gets quite low
and and also just it's I think it's a
brand new result just to be able to
learn anything about a distribution so
extreme
um
>> what is the the free energy there the
yaxis
>> the yaxis that is this coupled free
energy energy. So it's the
generalization of the free energy. And
again, the way it is is that as we go to
higher coupling values, it's more
sensitive to what's happening in the
tail of the distribution. So you can
think of it as like a robustness metric,
but at the same time, we've modified
what what samples we're drawing over in
order to make sure that this very
stringent metric can still converge.
Um now in order to do uh we we have then
looked at
um
metrics where we keep the metric
constant in order to do the um
head-to-head comparison. And here we see
what we would kind of expect is that we
get improvements in the accuracy. And
I'll call coupling equal to zero still a
accurate measurement. Whereas the
positive values of coupling I'll refer
to as robust metrics.
We do get um as we go from 10 the minus5
to 10 the minus2 we do get improvements
in the accuracy and throughout the whole
epic um we're getting an accurate model.
Um and that is up to I guess the I think
the darker one here is
um 10 to the 0. Oh actually say 10 to
the minus one is the darker one. Now
when we go to the Koshy distribution and
beyond the Koshy distribution we do see
that the accuracy metric with this free
energy does show decays in the
performance. So you in this case the
training has kind of a optimized
point very early in the epic cycles and
then as you continue to train it the
model actually gets worse with regard to
accuracy. Now that's not unexpected
because we weren't optimizing for the
accuracy. We were optimizing for
something else. Um and then the other
thing this is labeled incorrectly but
the um the last one here is the extreme
case of 10 to the five and it does show
that this extreme model has kind of
funky behavior and that that's sort of
typical of what would have been expected
but again I emphasize
without that use of the independent
equals the whole thing breaks down it
more like 10 to the uh 10 to the 0ero
here that was sort of the limit of the
prior results.
Now we also looked at how uh the
reconstruction fidelity is for this
um and the on the left is the original
samples in the middle is the uh
traditional VAE with the coupling equal
to zero and by eye you can maybe make
out a little bit of improvement with the
coupling value but the metrics are
actually quite impressive. Um so against
a metric known as the multiscale
structural similarity um we see 25%
improvement and that stays uh consistent
across all of the coupling values. So
even just a little bit of coupling
getting away from that the extremes
sharpness of the exponential tail right
away you get performance improvement and
that performance improvement stays
consistent across all the coupling
values that we used.
Um likewise um something called the
learn perceptual image patch similarity
had a 10% improvement.
Um and I guess okay so that that's it.
So
the conclusion here is that
we now have the ability to model the
most extreme distributions and we're
particularly um interested in how this
could be applied to catastrophic risk
modeling number one. uh but also I I
have a lot of scientific interest as in
terms of how it will improve active
inference for the following reason.
If you're going to measure errors in
every single node. So again just
remember the contrast here. Right now
the way machine learning algorithms are
trained is that you have one cost
function that's going to um be used to
modify the parameters of a large
network. Um
you can argue that in that situation
uh the Gaussian and the entropy
measurements
may be adequate for most use cases.
Maybe not one if you were trying to
model catastrophic risk, but for other
use cases, we've seen that it's very
powerful technique. This is the engine
of AI.
But in active inference, because you're
measuring errors at every single node,
you necessarily have very limited amount
of data characterizing those errors. And
that's exactly the original use case for
the student t distribution was that a
low amount of data corresponds to a low
degree of freedom.
And it's and that degree of freedom is
actually just the inverse of what I'm
calling the nonlinear statistical
coupling. So another way that these
models are grounded in traditional
statistics is that uh the nonlinear
coupling is just the inverse of the
degree of freedom.
So I think that in the active inference
models
um there's a real necessity for this
type of metric because there's a
necessity um to be able to
uh model accurately the fact that you're
trying to take these error measurements
over a limited amount of data.
and and the novelty here is to have both
a generalization of the metric in this
coupled logarithm
and a generalization of the samples
you're using with this independent
equals
um and new work that we're making
progress on is uh the theoretical proofs
um using information geome geometric
techniques you know that the this is
exactly the correct statistic Um,
and I'll also say like just for maybe
going to future reading here. So, I have
a preprint that's currently under review
that provides the proofs that there's a
unique scale called the independent
um
uh excuse me um that I refer to as
theformational scale that is required
for the modeling of heavy tail
distributions. And then from that
there's only one generalization of the
entropy function that gives you the
correct measurements. Um and so the
paper is called on the uniqueness of the
coupled entropy.
And this a variation of this
presentation was presented with a paper
at the um artificial general
intelligence conference 2025.
Um we have a new paper that's will have
more details coming out soon. Uh but the
original paper um from a few years ago
is called coupled vae and there we
showed improvements in the robustness
using these techniques. And then another
interesting paper I wrote several years
ago was a a book chapter um called
reduced perplexity which was a play on
words
um but it was showing this idea that you
can think of entropy as your measurement
of uncertainty along the y ais of a
distribution.
So with that I can uh thank you all. Uh
really appreciate the opportunity to
talk to this community, learn more about
what you're doing and looking forward to
some nice collaborations together.
>> Great.
>> Yeah. So people watching live can write
some questions. I'll ask some some
random things. So these are all central
tendency distributions.
How do you deal with situations where
you just are not mean centered around
zero?
>> Yeah. Okay. Excellent question. Um, so
alpha equal to one is the generalized
paro distribution which typically is a
one-sided distribution. Um, so that
could also be the model. Um and then um
with Uger Turkelli
we are doing um some research now in
which alpha is not equal to an integer
and those models have different kind of
characteristics. That's number one. The
other thing is that the family itself
includes that um H of X parameter. So
another generalization is what we call
the coupled wel distribution. So the
wyel distribution is another popular
one-sided
uh distribution from the exponential
family and then you can generalize that
with this coupled exponential. So we're
also looking at that as an interesting
case.
Yeah.
Okay.
Okay. Now,
>> I have um I'm happy to take questions
from the audience, but I have a question
for you, Dan. In your work on active
inference,
have you
noticed this feature that because you're
trying to learn at every node of a
network that you have difficulties with
the limited amount of data that each
node um experiences.
So
there's nothing about these models that
intrinsically has low or high amounts of
data. You could train a massive data set
on a single parameter
or or have a situation where there's
very little data. um
not always just a low number of data
points per parameter to learn like the
sort of large uh p small N issue, but
especially getting into thinking about
causal effects of action,
>> having world models or just having
generative models that have a lot of
conditional
aspects
makes it such that you will not have
data for a large number of conditional
aspects which sort of forces factorizing
or simplifying the problem back down to
simpler uh lower dimensional subpros.
M
>> and so the challenge would be well if
those lower dimensional subpros could be
solved but then you have even a lot of
combinotaurics of which smaller
dimensional subpros to tackle and again
if you knew the structure of the problem
then that is very tractable structure
learning. But then in a situation where
you might be dealing um with just
different kinds of data streams and not
necessarily have a well ststructured
world model then even that structure
learning problems becomes very
challenging.
>> Yeah. Uh well and yeah you actually
bring up another interesting use case
which is the curse of dimensionality. So
as you go to higher dimensions, this
issue of needing to use the heavy tails
to in order to make sure that your
models are more robust and more accurate
becomes more prominent.
Yeah.
>> On the heavy tails, I wondered, have you
thought about any of the physical
connections with the entropy? So there's
obviously more generalized
andformational entropies than
necessarily happening in a cup of water.
But how do these different tail
distributions,
for example, connect with temperature
distributions and thermal movements of
particles? Do they all follow one type
of tail distribution or do different
materials or different physical
situations
follow one of these differently?
>> Yeah, this is actually the heart of what
scientists in the field of complex
systems work very actively on and you
know thermodynamics grew out of modeling
equilibrium
u type things. So, so temperature for
instance is a measurement that re
basically has a requirement that you're
in equilibrium.
But of course, we're very interested in
being able to characterize nonequ
equilibrium systems
um or what can be called nonequilibrium
steadystate systems where it's not in
equilibrium but it does but the state
does persist over time. Um and there's a
lot of work in that area. Um this is a
big part of what motivated a field
called non-extensive statistical
mechanics that was originated by
Constantino Solace
and there's been proposals to generalize
thermodynamics using modified
entropy functions. Now I would argue but
it's not fully proved that mostly those
attempts have not been very successful.
They've had modest success, but they've
not really come up with a complete
model. And in this new paper, I have a
section showing that you do get a
you get a rigorous definition of the
temperature as being equal to this scale
parameter. Um and again this is another
thing that I think makes both the way
I'm characterizing the distributions and
this particular entropy function unique
it because I show that you can um that
basically that scale parameter is your
generalized temperature.
Um and the the interesting thing about
that calculation is that
uh in order to get that what came out of
the mathematics is that the free energy
function
um that underlies thermodynamics
it's that function that gets generalized
and has an additional nonlinear term in
it. Um and so that's where the
generalization comes and then the other
thing is I showed that there can be a
complimentary model where I can define
the temperature to be uh the scale
raised to a power related to that
coupling term.
Now my definition of temperature is more
complex and involves the nonlinearity.
But in that case then I can um have no
modifications to the free energy
equation. So there's also sort of this
interesting duality in terms of how you
build the models. But I think with that
result there's a strong case and it
would be very worthwhile for people to
look at whether the full laws of
thermodynamics can be generalized uh
using the coupled entropy.
So
back to to the data, it's interesting
that you highlight learning from little
data whereas almost one of the key
advantages is that you will not deflate
the variance when you have a lot of data
because the main issue is not
having a wide estimator on sparse data.
That's free. Mhm.
>> The hard thing is when you have a lot of
samples
not to just converge back to a training
data set. And that's why variational
methods and all other kinds of entropy
regularized
methods kind of are out there because
you don't want a collapse
simply to recapitulating the training
data or even narrower.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Well, I Yeah. You know it
was it's funny how just in the process
of working on these things you learn
a different connection. So
um
I have my background is in electrical
engineering and as part of that I've
studied both mathematics and physics
quite a bit. So I had not I would say a
strong background but certainly a
background in thermodynamic processes.
At the same time as we were um
developing the variational autoenccoder
we were learning about the importance of
the evidence lower bound and it's uh
basic way that it can be decomposed into
a measure of accuracy in your generative
process and then also a measure of the
regularization of making sure that you
using a simple model and that it's the
balance between these two things that's
important and ultimately what gives you
a good model. So it's not just accuracy
but it's accuracy with the simplest
model possible.
Now it was only through um it was only
through reading Carl Friston's work on
the active inference that I had this got
gained this understanding that the
evidence lower bound function is exactly
the free energy. And so there is a
direct connection between the
thermodynamics of complex systems and
the training of artificial general
intelligence and generative models. And
so I
as we as a team have been reading um
Parr and Kristen's new book on active
inference, it's been fascinating to see
just how general the concept is. And you
know again another thing that's exciting
for us is that we've mostly focused on
variational inference. And I six months
ago I was sort of expecting that as we
migrated to decision making and you know
kind of robotic control that that would
require a whole another set of
algorithms and a whole another set of
generalizations that we would have to
work on.
But now of course active inference has
integrated all of these techniques.
um you know so so now I I have a better
understanding that
um when it comes to action
you can think of your utility function
as just a prior distribution
and then what action you want to take
you can think of as an expected
um minimization of the free energy. So,
it's a beautiful representation and and
we're really excited about working on
these different kinds of problems.
>> Let's sort of foreshadow and head off on
one area that we've talked a little bit
about, which is when we're dealing with
causal models and structure learning,
we're in a little bit more of an
expanded setting than just like a
financial returns model. So in a
financial returns, we're dealing with
something that might be tightly
clustered or widely dispersed or have an
average trend or be zero centered on a
given fixed, you know, 24 hours
percentage change.
>> But and and as you get there's more and
more ways to be extreme and there's
fewer and fewer ways to be essentially
conformist.
Now when we open the door to cognitive
systems and multi-agent systems and
we're thinking about complex systems in
general. So there's more and more and
more and more ways that couplings
amongst actual subunits can interact.
So what what kinds of macro properties
or approaches
might help us bound
where we have uncertainty not just over
curtosis properties within a
distribution but where we actually have
a structural uncertainty about like
geospatial causal models.
So
I'll answer this a little bit indirectly
but I think something fascinating that
comes out of this is another core
principle in the active inference um
model is the idea of a marov blanket
where you separate your internal model
from the external model and then a
market blanket is where you declare
independence and and sort of
And and another way it can also be
thought of like one way you can think of
it as the markoff blanket between the
past, the now and the future, right? Um
well that's certainly foundational, but
one of the things that comes out of this
coupled algebra is the ability to relax
that assumption of independence.
Because if I apply now rather than a
markoff blanket, what I might refer to
as a coupled markoff blanket,
I am going to have independence in terms
of those correlation matrixes.
um but I'm going to have be able to
maintain a model in which there's
actually coupling uh across the blanket
that so so the coupling parameter is now
going to have be a way of storing
long-term correlation
um and I have done a little bit of work
on this in papers that either refer to
coupled markoff processes or coupled
basian processes
and and and at the heart of each of
these again the basian calculation is
similar. One of the basic assumptions in
basian analysis is that the prior
distribution gets multiplied by the
likelihood and then that gives you the
posterior distribution. Well, that
multiplication is assuming that the
prior and the likelihood are independent
of each other. But with the coupled
algebra, you can relax that and you um
you can have a a nonlinear coupling
between your prior state and your um
posterior state.
So for instance um
there's a scientist Topsoy who's used
that model in models of cognition
and and the way I think about his models
is sort of like
how
how strongly you care about your prior.
And so you you know you you you might be
a person that's sort of tied to a
particular set of beliefs, right? And no
amount of data is going to change those
beliefs.
And you can model that with this coupled
algebra. And and then vice versa. might
be someone who doesn't
have um you know
you're very loose in your priors and and
you're very loose in your beliefs and
you kind of then easily swayed by
whatever data comes in next and these
kind of differentials um are some of the
more interesting models that can be
created with this mathematics.
Now I don't think that answered your
question directly but uh it it but the
point is that there's much more subtle
kinds of causal models that can be
created uh using these techniques.
>> Well, I like the idea of the marov
blanket as the declaration of
independence. A fun idea and definitely
the attention to past, present, future
or just the marovian property of time
with the past influencing the future
>> through the present with this basian
moment of the intersection of how you
couple the prior and the likelihood. And
then also
in in in that it makes me think about
yes we could talk about all of the
interactions among subunits and there's
combinotaurics of structural
possibilities for the system of
interest. However, the variational
modeling agent
may have a much simpler model
that they would have more defined
properties of. So the estimators model
properties the map do not need to
recapitulate
actual structural adjacencies or aspects
of the world
and intelligence is about that kind of
basian information criteria or similar
driven approach to ride on that edge
with a dual imperative of accurate and
small.
>> Mhm.
Yeah. Ultimately, it is part of the goal
is to get simpler models. I I I agree
with that. And one one way you can
picture that is that if you have these
heavytail issues, one way you can get a
model still using the Gaussian is to
have a mixture of many Gaussians with
different uh variances, right? And and
so in a sense what the heavy tailed is
giving you is the ability to have one
distribution that can characterize
a a large mixture model of many Gaussian
uh distributions.
So, so it does, so I do think that as
you incorporate
the heavy tail into the the foundation
of these models, you'll also be able to
simplify how how many mixtures you need
in order to get a good characterization.
Just last comment or note here. Um what
what kind of software tooling or what
repos or which of the papers should
people explore
for if they wanted to get hands-on?
>> Um right. Um so the two papers on the
machine learning um have references to
our nonlinear statistical coupling and
CVAE uh repositories on git github.
Um, and we the the NSC library
um just uses a basic uh Python
tools
and then we originally did the work in
um
Tur um I'm TensorFlow and then we
migrated more recently to using PyTorch.
>> Cool. So I hope that people
>> walk through this and explore the
tooling and um
>> if there's anything else please feel
free to add it otherwise this has been
very uh interesting connect some of
these basic statistical principles basic
but advanced statistical principles to
some of the real situations that
embedded systems and intelligence
systems are finding with uh you know too
little too much data events that have
more variability than we have seen in
training data. These are issues that
beset all. So, it's awesome to see how
you're researching and applying that.
>> Yeah. Super. Thank you very much for the
invitation, Daniel.
>> Okay. Farewell. Bye.
>> Take care.